Guide to the William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana: Manuscripts
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Box and Folder List, 1542-1967; 7.51; (18 boxes)
  - LYSER, JOHANN PETER THEODOR, 1803-1870
    - ALS: Dresden, to R. Glaser, 1839 Aug 18 (Box 12, Folder 480)
      Glaser was editor of the periodical
      Ost und West, Prag.
      An urgent inquiry as to when his
      short story Der Mohr will appear.
      Lyser fears that the censor may
      object to it. It was published in
      Ost und West, 1840, no. 6-14.
  - LYTTON, E. G. E. LYTTON BULWER-LYTTON, 1803-1873
    Full name: Lytton, Edward George Earle
    Lytton Bulwer-Lytton, 1st baron.
    - Nine ALS, to Abraham Hayward, 1832-55 (Box 12, Folder 481)
      13 p.; various sizes.
      Written chiefly in his capacity as
      editor of The New Monthly magazine.
      Letters dated: Mar. 12, 1832 (1 p.,
      signed: ELB); Undated (1 p. with
      address, signed: ELB); Jul. 2, 1832
      (1 p. with address, signed: El
      Bulwer); Undated (2 p., signed: EBL)
      Undated (2 p., signed: EBL); Dec. 4,
      no year (2 p., signed: EBL); Undated
      (1 p., signed: EBL); Jun. 20, 1845
      (1 p., signed: EB Lytton); Mar. 1855
      (2 p., signed: EB Lytton).
      With: One mounted portrait and one
      caricature showing Bulwer Lytton,
      newspaper-clipping with biographical
      sketch and a clipping with article
      "Bulwer Lytton's life of misery with
      beautiful Irish girl" from "The
      Sunday News", London, Oct. 11, 1925,
      in the same folder.
    - ALS, to George Henry Lewes, 1843 Jan 28 (Box 12, Folder 482)
      An appreciation of Lewes' article on
      Goethe in the British and foreign
      quarterly.
    - ALS: Brighton, to George Henry Lewes?, 1843 Feb 11 (Box 12, Folder 483)
      3 p.; 11.5 x 18.5 cm.
      Requests Lewes' interpretation of two
      stanzas in Schiller's Das Ideal und
      das Leben.
    - AL (incomplete): Indy P. Line, to George Henry Lewes, 1865 Feb (Box 12, Folder 484)
      13 p.; 11 x 18 cm.
      Chiefly an appreciation of G. H.
      Lewes' work, Life of Goethe.
  - MACGOWAN, JOHN, 1726-1780
    - ALS: Edinburgh, to William Shenstone, 1760 Jun 21 (Box 12, Folder 485)
      3 p.; 19 x 22.5 cm.
  - MCMULLAN, FRANK ALONZO, 1907-
    - An interpretation and a production of Goethe's Faust, [1949] (Box 13, Folder 486)
      1 p.l., 2-36 numb.l.; 28 cm.
      Typescript (original and xerox)
      Copy of a proposed article on the
      production of Faust, pt.I, at the
      Yale Drama school, during the week
      of March 20, 1949; the production
      was based on the translation of
      Alice Raphael, and under the
      direction of the author.
  - MALTITZ, APOLLONIUS FREIHERR VON, 1795-1870
    - ALS: Karlsbad, to Rudolf Glaser, 1844 Oct 10 (Box 13, Folder 487)
      4 p.; 14.5 x 23.5 cm.
      Headpiece: Schlossbrunn, Marktbrunn,
      Neubrunn.
      Enclosure: An autograph poem, signed:
      Wiedersehen mit Karlsbad, 2 p.
      20 x 25 cm.
    - ALS: Weimar, to Rudolf Glaser, 1845 Mar 19 (Box 13, Folder 488)
  - MARSHALL, JAMES
    - ALS: Weimar, to Bayard Taylor, 1874 Jul 6 (Box 13, Folder 489)
      2 p.; 14 x 22 cm.
      Enclosure: A letter from Princess
      Elisabeth of Saxe-Weimar-Eisenach,
      dated July 3, 1874, in which she
      expresses her appreciation of the
      photographs of Mr. and Mrs. Taylor,
      is in Box 3, folder 131.
  - MARTIN, SIR THEODORE, 1816-1909
    - ALS: London, to Prof. Edward A. Dowden, 1866 Nov 28 (Box 13, Folder 490)
      "I send you by book post the volume
      [Poems; Original and Translated, by
      Theodore Martin, London, Printed
      for private circulation, 1863]
      which contains my translation of a
      portion of the Second part of
      Faust. Whether I shall ever
      complete my version is very
      doubtful."
    - ALS: 31 Onslow Square, to Hermann Kindt, 1865 Mar 28 (Box 13, Folder 491)
      With impressed seal.
      Enclosure: Twenty-seven lines from
      Martin's translation of Goethe's
      Faust, pt.I, beginning "Him who
      dares name", dedicated to Hermann
      Kindt.
      Kindt is the author of Goethe's Faust
      in England, 1874.
    - ALS: Manchester, to Hermann Kindt, 1866 Oct 27 (Box 13, Folder 492)
    - ALS: London, to Mssrs. Wittingham and Wilkins, 1865 Nov 3 (Box 13, Folder 493)
      2 p.; 11.5 x 18.5 cm.
      "I enclose my cheque for £ 67 in
      payment of your account for
      printing "Faust". The publishers
      tell me I must go to press at
      once with a Second edition."
      The title was Faust, part I, A
      Dramatic Poem, by Goethe.
      Edinburgh and London, 1865.
  - MATHEWS, CHARLES JAMES, 1803-1878
    - ALS: Pelham Crescent, to Frederick Gye?, 1864 Jun 23 (Box 13, Folder 494)
      2 p.; 11.5 x 17.5 cm.
  - MEISSNER, ALFRED, 1822-1885
    - Autograph poem "Im Dome von Alfred Meissner", Prag, 1839 Nov 6 (Box 13, Folder 495)
      The title is corrected from
      "Schlaflose Nächte."
      The date is crossed out.
      22 verses of 4 lines each.
      With: Autograph poem "Im Dome,"
      2 p.; 18 cm., 10 verses of 4 lines
      the first verse is the same as the
      last of the preceding poem.
      With: ALS to unnamed correspondent,
      Aug. 7, 1870, 2 p.; 22 cm.
  - MEJER, JOHANN WILHELM, 1789-1871
    - ALS: Clausthal, to Johann Peter Eckermann?, 1831 Oct 30 (Box 13, Folder 496)
  - MELUSINE
    - Die schöne Melusine, Buchholz, 1890 Dec 5 (Box 13, Folder 497)
      AMs, 127 p.; 17 x 20 cm.
      Transcribed by Arthur Neumeister.
      On inner front cover:
      "Handschriftliches Originaltextbuch
      des Puppenspielers Arthur
      Neumeister. (1890). Von Amalie Apel
      gek[auft]. G. Ehrhardt."
  - MEYER, HANS HEINRICH, 1760-1832
    - ALS: Weimar, to Heinrich Karl Abraham Eichstädt, 1806 Nov 22 (Box 13, Folder 498)
      1 p.; 16.5 x 20 cm.
    - ALS: Weimar, to Gottlieb Hufeland?, 1815 Jan 21 (Box 13, Folder 499)
      4 p.; 13.5 x 17.5 cm.
  - MEYER, HEINRICH, 1904-1977
    - Goethe - Love and poetry ... A talk to the assembly of Clark University (Box 13, Folder 500)
      11 l.; 28 cm.
      Probably published - CFS.
    - Literature and science of Goethe's day; a library collected by Heinrich Meyer, 1952 (Box 13, Folder 501)
      5 p. l., 59 numb. l.; 29 cm.
      Caption-title.
  - MEYER, JOACHIM
    - ALS: Nuremberg, to Johann Peter Eckermann, 1842 Jun 18 (Box 13, Folder 502)
      1 p.; 21.5 x 27 cm.
  - MOLTKE, HELMUTH KARL BERNHARD, GRAF VON, 1800-1891
    - ALS (Copy in A.H. Hoffmann von Fallersleben's handwriting): Crisau, to A.H. Hoffmann von Fallersleben, 1873 Oct 26 (Box 13, Folder 503)
      1 p.; 8 x 15 cm.
      "Dem gefeierten Sänger in Schloss
      Corveÿ meinen herzlichen Dank in
      Prosa, für Verse, die ihm keiner
      nachmacht, Gr. Moltke,
      Feldmarschall.
  - MORGENSTERN, KLARA
    - Commonplace book, [1866?] (Box 13, Folder 504)
      AMs, 8 l.; 21 x 17 cm.
      Bound in pink boards with label:
      Clara Morgenstern. I. Cl.
      Miscellaneous poems and prose
      passages; incl. "Depositenschein"
      for the sum of 500 Gulden to be
      held for Gottlieb Kaiser, dated
      Fürth, den 27. März 1866.
      Each item signed: Klara [or K.]
      Morgenstern.
  - MORRISON, LEWIS, 1844?-1906
    - ALS: Harrisburg, to Mrs. Johnson, 1874 Sep 24 (Box 13, Folder 505)
      4 p.; 12.5 x 20.5 cm.
    - Autograph quotation from Goethe's Faust, 1.Th. signed, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 506)
      1 p.; 22 x 28 cm.
      Letterhead in grey and red with
      legend: "Lewis Morrison as Mephisto
      in Faust, the grandest production
      on the American stage."
  - MOTLEY, JOHN LOTHROP, 1814-1877
    Commonplace-book. [1838?]
    - 181, 12 p.; 19 x 24 cm. AMs., with notes on Goethe on p. 28-48. The book consists of 303 leaves of which 401 pages are numbered. Handwritten notes in English, German or French, on 181 pages, with 12 pages of index at end. Clippings pasted in on 11 pages. 9 leaves torn or cut out. Miss A. E. Chaney: "The personality of Goethe as reflected in the American magazines before 1860," (Master's Essay, 1927, unpublished), proves Motley's authorship on the basis of the notes in the commonplace book. These Goethe notes represent the rough material for the article which appeared in the New York Review, 1839.
    - See: Bound Volumes, folder 822
  - MÜFFLING, F. K. F. FREIHERR VON, 1755-1851
    Full name: Müffling, Friedrich Karl
    Ferdinand Freiherr von.
    - ALS: Weimar, to Karl Emil Spiegel?, 1840 Sep 3 (Box 13, Folder 507)
  - MÜLLER, FRIEDRICH VON, 1779-1849
    - ALS: Weimar, to Bernhard Rudolf Abeken, 1832 Jun 10 (Box 13, Folder 508)
      The enclosure, von Müller's Epilog,
      written on the occasion of the
      memorial exercises for Goethe's
      death, not present.
      This letter pub. in Allgemeine
      Zeitung, Beilage, 1905, no. 74 and
      75, in his article: Sieben Briefe
      des Kanzlers von Müller an Abeken.
    - ALS: Weimar, to Bernhard Rudolf Abeken, 1835 Mar 29 (Box 13, Folder 509)
      Outlines the background of the
      struggle to convince the Kestner
      family to publish the correspondence
      between Charlotte Kestner and
      Goethe. It was finally pub. in 1854
      with title Goethe und Werther.
      This letter pub. in Allgemeine Zeitung,
      Beilage, 1905, no. 74 and 75, in his
      article: Sieben Briefe des Kanzlers
      von Müller an Abeken.
    - ALS: Weimar, to Bernhard Rudolf Abeken, 1838 Feb 22 (Box 13, Folder 510)
      4 p.; 20 x 26 cm.
      Thanking him for the gift of several
      transcriptions of Justus Möser's
      essays. Goethe's correspondence with
      Knebel is ready for printing; also
      Goethe's correspondence with Count
      Reinhard.
    - ALS: Weimar, to Bernhard Rudolf Abeken, 1842 Jul 13 (Box 13, Folder 511)
      Müller thanks him for the gift of J.
      Möser's works in 10 vols., which
      Abeken has edited. By way of a
      slight return Müller encloses his
      article "Zum Gedächtnis: Johann
      Karl Ludwig von Schorn."
      Beilage, 1905, no. 74 and 75 in his
    - ALS: Weimar, to Bernhard Rudolf Abeken, 1845 Mar 20 (Box 13, Folder 512)
      4 p.; 22 x 28 cm.
      Enclosure: Printed poem "Auf dem
      Gikelhahn bei Ilmenau, am 28.
      August 1838, von Fr. von Müller
      und Genast."
    - LS: Weimar, to Bernhard Rudolf Abeken, 1847 Feb 4 (Box 13, Folder 513)
      Writer unidentified.
    - LS: Weimar, to Bernhard Rudolf Abeken, 1849 Oct 6 (Box 13, Folder 514)
    - ALS, to Carl Gustav Carus?, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 515)
    - ALS: Weimar, to Carl Gustav Carus?, 1832 Apr 5 (Box 13, Folder 516)
      5 p.; 21 x 26 cm.
    - ALS: Weimar, to Heinrich Karl Abraham Eichstädt?, 1834 Feb 28 (Box 13, Folder 517)
      2 p.; 22.5 x 27 cm.
    - ALS: Weimar, to Heinrich Karl Abraham Eichstädt?, 1834 Apr 10 (Box 13, Folder 518)
      1 p.; 13 x 21.5 cm.
    - ... Auf dem Gikelhahn bei Ilmenau, am 28. August 1838. Von Fr. von Mueller und Genast
      - p. 182-3; 21.5 cm. Printed poem enclosed in F. v. Müller's letter to Abeken.
      - IN: F. v. Müller's letter to Abeken Box 13, folder 512
    - Autograph receipt, signed, Weimar, 1833 Dec 29 (Box 13, Folder 519)
      As agent for Countess Caroline von
      Egloffstein, von Müller signs as
      having received her pension for the
      quarter Michaelis - Christmas.
  - MÜLLER, FRIEDRICH MAX, 1823-1900
    - ALS: Oxford, to Theodor Nöldeke, 1872 Oct 15 (Box 13, Folder 520)
      On stationery with black border.
  - MÜLLER, GUSTAV ADOLF, 1866-1928
    - 3 ALS: Strassburg, to Jacob Anton Leyser, 1894 (Box 13, Folder 521)
      15 p.; 17 x 11 cm.
      Letters dated: Mar. 22, 27 and Aug.
      31, 1894.
      Removed from Gustav Adolf Müller,
      Sesenheim, wie es ist, Bühl, 1894.
      The Yale copy is inscribed by the
      author to Dr. J. Leyser.
  - MÜLLER, KARL LUDWIG METHUSALEM, 1771-1837
    - ALS: Leipzig, to Heinrich Carl Friedrich Peucer, 1828 Sep 12 (Box 13, Folder 522)
    - Empty folder (Box 13, Folder 523)
  - MÜLLER, WALTRAUD
    - Goethe. 12 poems, n.d.
      - AMs, 21 p.; 36 x 25 cm. Written in Gothic letters; title in gold, red initials. Contents: Heidenröslein; Gleich und Gleich; Freudvoll und leidvoll; Erinnerung; Wer nie sein Brot mit Tränen ass [from Wilhelm Meister]; Feiger Gedanken bängliches Schwanken; Volk und Knecht und Überwinder [from West-östlicher Divan]; An den Mond; Das Göttliche; Eigenthum; Zum Sehen geboren; Wenn im Unendlichen [Zahme Xenien].
      - See: Oversize: Box 19, folder 831b
  - NANGLE, BENJAMIN CHRISTIE, 1901-
    - A descriptive bibliography of the articles relating to German literature which appeared in the Ediburgh Review and The Quarterly Review before the year 1836 (Box 13, Folder 524)
      8, 13, 13 p.; 28 cm.
      Typescript with a few corrections.
  - NEDILA, KATHARINA E.
    - The William A. Speck Collection at Yale University, 1967 (Box 13, Folder 525)
      10 l.; 28 cm.
      Typescript (Xerox copy)
      A term paper in library science
      course at Columbia University,
      Summer, 1967.
  - NESTROY, JOHANN
    - Die schlimmen Buben. Posse mit Gesang in 1 Acte von Joh. N. Nestroy. Musik vom Kapellmeister Adolf Müller senior, n.d.
      AMs, 146 p.; 19 cm.
      On label on cover: Nestroy. Die
      schlimmen Buben. Scenarion. (1886).
      2 photographs of Johann Nestroy
      mounted on 1 leaf inserted between
      p. 76 and 77.
      Without music.
      Published in Nestroy's Gesammelte
      Werke, 1890-91.
  - NEUMEISTER, ARTHUR
    - ALS: Glashütte i.La.?, to Georg Ehrhardt, 1905 Sep 4
      - 1 p.; 23 cm. Enclosure (slips) wanting. Announcing shipment of two books: Melusine and Robert der Teufel.
      - IN: Faust puppet-play, Box 3, folder 150.
    - ALS: Glashütte i.La., to Georg Ehrhardt, 1905 Sep 23
      - 1 p.; 22 cm. Enclosure: Postal money order slip. No offers of puppet-play texts received on two advertisements in "Der Komet." Gives addresses of Bonesky and the Widow Apel.
      - IN: Faust puppet-play, Box 3, folder 150
  - NEUREUTHER, EUGEN NAPOLEON, 1806-1882
    - ALS: Munic, to Monsieur!, 1835 Apr 24 (Box 13, Folder 527)
      1 p.; 19 x 24 cm.
      In French.
  - NICOLAI, CHRISTOPH FRIEDRICH, 1733-1811
    - ALS: Berlin, to Johann Christian Gaedicke, 1801 Jan 26 (Box 13, Folder 528)
      1 p.; 17.5 x 20 cm.
  - NORTON, CHARLES ELIOT, 1827-1908
    - ALS: Cambridge, Mass., to Mr. Chadwick, 1898 Oct 20 (Box 13, Folder 529)
      4 p.; 17 x 11 cm.
      Letter discusses the interpretation
      of stanzas 19-20 of Matthew
      Arnold's poem "The scholar gipsy."
  - OESER, FRIEDERIKE, 1748-1829
    - ALS: Leipzig, to "Meine theure Freundin" Jettchen, 1828 Jul 10 (Box 13, Folder 530)
  - PAGANINI, NICCOLO, 1782-1840
    - Power of attorney, printed form, filled in and signed, Frankfurt, 1830 Mar 9 (Box 13, Folder 531)
      1 p.; 21 x 31 cm.
      Paganini legally appoints Dr.
      Reinganum to act for him in all
      matters.
      With a sheet entitled "Paganini, in
      Weimar" containing 5 pictures of
      the artist in different poses,
      issued by A. Böhme.
  - PALMER, ARTHUR HUBBELL, 1859-1918
    - Johann Wolfgang Goethe. A Comemorative[!] Address, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 532)
      AMs, 57 l.; 26 x 21 cm.
      Arthur H. Palmer was professor and
      chairman of the German department
      at Yale University, 1891-1916.
  - PATON, SIR JOSEPH NOEL, 1821-1901
    - Autograph quotation from Goethe in Eng. tr., Edinburgh, 1895 Aug (Box 13, Folder 533)
      1 p. (5 lines); 18 x 11 cm.
      Impressed letter head: 33 George
      Square, Edinburgh.
      Signed: Noël Paton.
  - PATTISON, JACOB HENRY
    - Autograph biographical memoir of Henry Crabb Robinson, 1864 Oct (Box 13, Folder 534)
      10 p.; 24 cm.
      "Biographical memoir written by my
      father J. H. Pattison - J.L.P."
      written on last leaf.
  - PEEL, LADY EMILY (HAY)
    - ALS: Whitehall, to Frederick Gye, 1864 May 23 (Box 13, Folder 535)
  - PENNY, GEORGE B.
    Schiller's ballads discussed as ballads
    and as poems. Compared with Goethe's
    ballads, etc. Sketch of the ballad. 1884
    - AMs, signed, 44 p.; 26 x 20 cm. Clippings from a printed collection of Schiller's ballads in English translation, inserted. The essay was written for Professor H. S. White during Spring Term at Cornell University.
    - See: Bound Volumes, folder 823
  - PERCIVAL, JAMES GATES, 1795-1856
    - Manuscript lecture notes, some fragmentary, addressed to the New Haven Sing-Song Club, on German and Scandinavian poems; together with manuscript text of his translations or imitations of some of these poems, and of some original poems (Box 13, Folder 536)
      11 pieces; various sizes.
  - PERFALL, KARL THEODOR EMANUEL BARON VON, 1824-1907
    - ALS: Munich, to Dr. Carl Gille, 1866 Feb 24 (Box 13, Folder 537)
      1 p.; 23 x 29 cm.
      Letterhead: Die Königliche Bayerische
      Hof-Musik-Intendanz.
      "Seine Majestät der König hat die
      Aufführung der Faustsymphonie von
      Franz Liszt anzubefehlen geruht."
      Perfall requests Gille to have the
      necessary scores sent immediately
      to Munich.
      With: ALS: Munich, to Dr. Carl Gille
      May 17, 1866. 1 p.; 23 x 29 cm.
      Same letterhead as above. Perfall
      returns with thanks the
      "Orchesterstimmen zum
      Mephistowalzer sowie die Chorstimmen
      zur Faustsymphonie."
  - PEUCER, HEINRICH CARL FRIEDRICH, 1779-1849
    - ALS: Weimar, to "Verehrtester Freund", 1826 Mar 9 (Box 13, Folder 538)
    - ALS, to Philipp Karl Christian Sondershausen (Box 13, Folder 539)
      1 p.; 10 x 15 cm.
  - PICKARD, SAMUEL THOMAS, 1828-1915
    - 2 ALS: Andover, Mass. & Boston, to William A. Speck, 1903 May 29 (Box 13, Folder 540)
      1903 Apr 8
      3 p.; 14 x 23 cm.
      Enclosure: Autograph note "The
      Erlking," 1 p.; 20 x 24 cm.
      Mr. Speck notes at bottom of sheet:
      "Written by S. T. Pickard.
      Newspaper clipping referred to was
      evidently lost."
      Both letters and note deal with the
      provenance of the Whittier
      manuscript of the Erlking
      translation.
  - PICKERING, AMELIA
    - Receipt, signed, to Mrs. Baker, 1788 Feb 23 (Box 13, Folder 541)
      1 p.; 6 x 15 cm.
      Signed: A. Pickering.
      Printed form filled in ms.: Received
      of Mrs. Baker the sum of One Guinea
      ... for two copies of The Sorrows
      of Werter ... There were in all 961
      subscribers, Mrs. Baker held
      receipt no. 344.
  - PNIOWER, OTTO, B. 1859
    - ALS, to Professor Carl Frederick Schreiber, 1901 Jun 21 (Box 13, Folder 542)
      1 p.; 9 x 12 cm.
  - POELSKE, KARL, 1881-
    - ALS: Berlin, to Herr Beb, 1919 Jan 2 (Box 13, Folder 543)
      Concerns an evening lecture on the
      subject of revolution and lyrical
      poetry and referring to a passage
      in Goethe on the same topic.
      An announced enclosure is not present.
  - PORTER, MARTHA DAY, 1838-1922
    - ALS: 31 Hillhouse Avenue, New Haven, 1894 Jul 16 (Box 14, Folder 544)
      Signed in the same handwriting: Martha
      Day Porter, Rebecca Taylor Porter.
      Directing their executor to give their
      copy of Schiller's Wallenstein,
      translated by Coleridge, autographed
      by Wadsworth, to Rev. Wm. B. Clarke,
      Yale 1849, Durham Conn., or to his
      daughters Helen MacGregor Clarke and
      Jane Baker Clarke.
      Removed from J. C. F. v. Schiller,
      Wallenstein, translated by S. T.
      Coleridge, London, 1800, in the Speck
      Collection.
  - POST, CHARLOTTE
    Autograph cook-book. 1822 Jun 28
    - 85 p.; 16 cm. A collection of recipes, begun by Charlotte Post, whose autograph is on fly-leaf, and continued by various other writers. Includes 12 p. at end, where the notation of recipes has been resumed. 4 small mss., further recipes in various hands, in envelope tipped in at end.
    - See: Bound Volumes, folder 824
  - PRELLER, FRIEDRICH JOHANN CHRISTIAN ERNST, 1804-1878
    - ALS, : Italy?, to Frau Sylli Kämpfer (Box 14, Folder 545)
  - PÜCKLER-MUSKAU, H. L. H., FÜRST VON, 1785-1871
    Full name: Pückler-Muskau, Hermann Ludwig
    Heinrich, Fürst von, 1785-1871.
    - ALS: Muskau, Ober-Lausitz, to "Ew Wohlgebohren", 1817 Apr 20 (Box 14, Folder 546)
      1 p.; 25 x 19 cm.
      An inquiry whether F. A. M. Retzsch
      would sell his original drawings
      illustrating Goethe's Faust.
  - PUPPENSPIEL
    - Parodie der Schülerszene aus Goethes Faust. Aufgeführt auf der Kneipe zu Ehren des ersten Karl Schurz Professors Dr. Eugen Kühnemann, 1912 Oct 1 (Box 14, Folder 547)
      9 numb. l.; 28 cm.
      With: Carbon of same typescript.
  - QUANDT, JOHANN GOTTLOB VON, 1787-1859
    - ALS: Leipzig, to Johann Heinrich Meyer?, 1815 Nov 9 (Box 14, Folder 548)
      2 p.; 18 x 20 cm.
      Thanking him for a report on certain
      pictures, and a request to receive
      cordially Baron von Beineburgh.
  - RABE, IRMGARD
    - Zu Staufen steht ein Wirtshaus, 1913 Nov 22 (Box 14, Folder 549)
      Green paper wrapper.
      At head of first line: Melodie: Am
      Brunnen vor dem Tore.
      Written in commemoration of the
      dedication of the Faust room in the
      Gasthof zum Löwen at Staufen.
  - RABE, MAX
    - Vorspiel im Himmel. Der Herr-(Goethe), die weimarischen Heerscharen, nachher Faust, Leipzig, 1914 Mar 4 (Box 14, Folder 550)
      AMs, signed, 7 p.; 21 cm.
      A parody on the "Vorspiel im Himmel"
      in Goethe's Faust, part I.
  - RADEBERG, GERMANY, STADTRAT
    - ADS: Radeberg, to Frau Amalie verw. Apel, 1911 Apr 8
      - 1 p.; 17 x 21 cm. folded to 17 x 10 cm. Permit to produce marionette shows.
      - IN: Faust puppet-play, Bound volumes, folder 801
  - RAMLER, KARL WILHELM, 1725-1798
    - An Mademoiselle Beckerinn bey ihrer Durchreise durch Berlin, Berlin, 1784 Aug 12 (Box 14, Folder 551)
      2 p.; 8 x 13 cm.
      Begins: "Mit Recht wünscht."
      On p. [2] another poem: "An
      ebendieselbe von ebendemselben,"
      beginning: "Durch die vollkommenste
      Dorothea."
    - Ode an Ihro Königliche Hoheit die Prinzessin Amalia bey unterthänigster Uberreichung der Passions-Cantate [Tod Jesu], die nach dero höchsteigenhändigen Angabe verfertiget worden, 1754 (Box 14, Folder 552)
      AMs, 4 p.; 18 x 21 cm.
      Begins: "Vom gantzen Walde wählt mein
      Lied."
      The music to the cantata, which
      according to Allgemeine deutsche
      Biographie was never printed, was
      composed by Johann Gottlieb Graun.
      Princess Amalia was the sister of
      Frederick the Great.
      Published in Ramler's Lyrische
      Gedichte, 1772.
  - REHBEIN, WILHELM, D. 1825
    - ALS: Weimar, to Christian Gottfried Nees von Esenbeck, 1824 Mar 31 (Box 14, Folder 553)
      3 p.; 12 x 20 cm.
      Rehbein, Goethe's physician, goes
      into detail on Goethe's severe
      illness during the winter of
      1823-24.
  - REINBOLD, ADELHEID, 1800-1839
    Masaniello, Eine Julywoche des Jahres
    1647. Dramatische Novelle, nach Quellen
    bearbeitet von Wilhelm Hof [pseud.]. n.d.
    - AMs, 366 p.; 27 x 21 cm. Green half-leather binding. "Wilhelm Hof" on t.p. crossed off, "Franz Berthold," another pseudonym used by the author, pencilled below. The author was a friend of Tieck. She sent the ms. to Rotteck under the name of W. Hof; it was thought to be lost and has never been published or described. - Note on Mr. von Faber's old catalogue card. Cf. Edith Gilmore, Masaniello in German literature; Thesis, Ph.D., Yale University, 1950.
    - See: Bound Volumes, folder 825
    - Saul, Trauerspiel in fünf Aufzügen. n.d.